Recovering addicts sponsored by Emmanuel TV at the Lighthouse Recovery Center
We are thankful for this opportunity to be here with a very special brother.
Brother, can you first tell us your name?
Timothy.
We thank you, Emmanuel TV because this gives us the opportunity to hear from other people.
Their testimonies help reroute people who are going through rough times in life.
Brother, can you tell us a little bit about yourself?
As a kid, I grew up with my grandmother and I was really sheltered.
I never even heard a curse word.
When I was 11, she passed away.
After she passed away, I had to go and live with my mother.
Living there was a total environment change.
When I opened her closet, I would see 200 to 300 pounds of drugs.
It was her husband and hers.
There were guns around and there was violence.
How old were you?
I was 11 years old.
I was scared and didn’t know how to take it – the violence at home.
I ran away the week after I turned 13.
When I ran away, it was hard.
I became a petty thief and went on to what I saw at my mother’s house – drugs.
I did a lot of things with drugs and I made an older friend.
While hanging out with him, I learned a very important lesson quickly.
That is not to judge people on the streets because it is bad.
I hung out with him for about a year and half.
I would have bet everything I had in life that he would never be violent.
One day, we were in a situation where he pulled out a gun and shot somebody in front of me.
I was wrong.
That was a lesson I learnt because I was on the streets.
After that, it became a recurring thing.
He shot so many people in front of me, I thought it was normal.
Living in that background, I thought it was legal.
I’ve got gangster tattoos all over my arms.
Somehow, I went from an inspired kid to having my motivation change; I wanted to be a gangster.
About 25, that was when I really started carrying a gun.
I actually started carrying it when I was 20 but I didn’t understand what I was doing.
When I was 25, I started putting it to work.
Friends that I knew started noticing me and what I was doing.
They came to me and wanted me to collect some money for them.
The amount I collected went up; it went up to a couple thousand dollars, then 6,000-7,000 dollars.
The next thing I knew, it was 15,000 to 50,000 dollars.
I have always been a little guy.
For me to walk up to someone and expect them to pay their debts -
they already knew that the people they were messing with were no joke.
I had to put a little more use to the gun.
So, what does that mean?
What did you end up having to do?
I shot a lot of people.
I wasn’t a killer but with my common sense, I could say that I was always smart.
Maybe I wasn’t smart at that time but I felt like I could shoot someone in the foot
to get my point across and I didn’t have to worry about anyone dying.
I would shoot them in their hand or whatever it may be.
So, that was what I started doing.
Let me ask you this; how did that affect you?
How did it come back upon you?
Did you end up facing death at some point?
Yes, over the years as my name got bigger and bigger
and I started grabbing more money for people, I ended up getting shot.
I have been shot five different times.
I got shot right between my eyes by a 9mm gun from five feet away.
You were shot by a 9mm gun right between the eyes?
Right here is where it went in.
Behind the forehead, there is a plate that protects the brain.
It went through my forehead, hit the plate, went down and broke my jaw,
went back up through my eye, shattered my eye socket and then the bullet went into my temple.
Pieces of the bullet are still in there now.
I checked out of the hospital three days later and was right back at it.
I took a bullet like a trophy.
When I set my mind on something, I went for it.
At that time, I was building a reputation; I was one of the toughest guys in the area.
The enemy would actually blind us to even death; where we not even fear death that much.
I had no fear of death; I accepted it.
I got so deep in it that I accepted it.
Tell me now what led you here to the Lighthouse.
One day, I received a letter and this letter was crystal clear.
This letter was talking about God and how good life is.
It brought me to tears.
When I got out of prison, the Lighthouse Recovery Center accepted me.
When I came here, it was hard at first to adjust
because I was coming from a circle full of very dark people.
How long have you been here?
I have been here for six and a half months now.
When I got here, I picked up the Bible and started doing one-on-one therapy.
I realised all the errors in my thinking.
I just worked really hard and now I am in leadership.
Emmanuel TV is sponsoring us here at the Lighthouse Recovery Center.
This place is changing lives.
It’s not like every other rehab or drug programme.
This one involves God and I believe that is a very important thing.
It involves God and we are recovering; all things are possible.
Recovering addicts sponsored by Emmanuel TV at the Lighthouse Recovery Center
We are here, at the Lighthouse Recovery Center.
We've got a very special brother.
This is an encouragement to all young people going through challenges.
Determination is what it takes to change your life.
Brother, tell me your name.
I'm Matthew.
I heard a very encouraging story about you.
Tell me a little bit about yourself and what led you to the Lighthouse.
When you become a part of the life of drugs and alcohol,
you find yourself walking around aimlessly.
At one point in my life, I had everything.
I had a wife; I had a son named Joshua.
All of that got taken away from me because of my choice to go to the world and do the wrong thing.
Depression really crept in and I found myself walking across intersections
because I just wanted to end my life.
I closed my eyes and just hoped that as I was walking across an intersection,
somebody would just run me over.
I did that on a daily basis.
But God didn’t allow that to happen.
I heard about the Lighthouse Recovery Center in a way that gave me hope.
I knew that if I could make it here, I could start afresh
and do something different with my life,
even though everything was taken away from me.
I had known God before and I knew He could do it again.
I knew that if I could make it here, I could breathe again.
So, what did it mean? Somebody went and picked you up, or somebody flew you out here?
Tell me what happened.
I was in Lexington, Kentucky.
I ended up in Lexington, Kentucky due to an extradition of child support -
neglecting to pay my child support.
They let me out within a week but it left me homeless in Lexington.
That was where depression really set in because I had nobody to call.
I knew if I could make it here, I would be alright.
How far is Lexington from here?
It’s about a three and a half hour car trip and I walked it.
Three and a half hour car-trip; and you walked all the way here - so it means walking...
...for 54 hours.
You walked 54 hours just to get here.
Yes.
Emmanuel! God is with us!
Now, this brother is here and his life is changed.
This is the reason it is so important for us to support ministries like this.
So, Emmanuel TV and Partners, thank you for your support.
Thank you, my brother.
Emmanuel. We are still here at the Lighthouse Recovery Center.
I've got a very special guest with us right now.
I'm just going to get him to start by telling us his name, and give us a little bit of his background,
his upbringing, challenges in life, and what led him here to the Lighthouse.
First, I will start by asking your name.
Brother, what's your name?
I'm Jamie.
Where are you from?
I'm from Bloomington, Indiana.
Let us know; we know that you are here at the Lighthouse,
and we heard that you are a very important part of Lighthouse.
Can you tell us a little bit about your background, and what led you here?
In John 5, you have the man at the pool of Bethesda.
Jesus didn’t just heal the man and tell him to get up and walk
but it was very significant that He told him to take his mat and walk.
It was a symbol of what he was delivered from.
Some of the things I was delivered from and got out of,
I now lift up as a testimony of what God can deliver others from.
I grew up very roughly – in a criminal lifestyle and drug culture.
At the age of 18, I went to prison for murder.
I spent the past 23 years incarcerated for the charge of murder.
It was while incarcerated that I encountered some of the outreach ministries.
That’s how I became acquainted with the Lighthouse Recovery Center.
There are numbers of secular recovery places that deal with addiction and compulsion
but they are missing that spiritual component – that God-shaped hole.
This is that wholeness;
this is what is going to bring us back to that balance.
What would lead a person to feel like they have to defend themselves or commit murder?
I know this is a very hard question, but what would you say is the root of a problem like that?
There may be someone out there that has anger or outburst.
What would you say to them?
Because you’ve been through it and now you have come out of it
so you can help lead someone out.
I know it is a hard question but it is so real.
As a youth, I saw it in myself.
Reflecting back, I see that there are so many today that lack that soundness,
that appropriate fathering in an active sense.
They are really being fed, nurtured and reared as men in that setting.
The spiritual component is lacking.
I would say that this is where things like Christian fathering programmes, parenting programmes
and being ‘churched’ in a verb, in an action sense, being poured into and invested in -
those inadequacies – I felt and I see it in so many others, especially in our youth.
Now you were saying that when it comes to youth,
you see a lot of them trying to manoeuvre through life
and trying to make it on their own the best way they know how.
Emmanuel TV Talks To Recovering Addicts At The Lighthouse Recovery Center
Getting back to the God-shaped hole in their heart,
they are trying to take so many things from the secular world, violence and the drug culture.
It is a square peg in a round hole.
It’s not fitting; it’s not working.
We have responses like the incarceration rates, rates of addiction, suicide
and recidivism rates for people that are returning to incarceration and staying in that cycle.
This is the answer – things that are Christ-centered:
recovery from addictions; training, discipling and really fathering
from ultimate Fathering down into men, sons, women and daughters.
This is the solution.
In addition to drug addiction and alcoholism was hatred.
I was a member in a capacity of leadership for a number of years,
in the Indiana Department of Corrections with the Aryan (White) Brotherhood.
I was delivered from that in addition to addiction.
It is sin and it’s a sin that you spread and contaminate others with.
To be delivered from that, to have that lifted off,
for that weight to be gone and be replaced with love -
that stony-hard heart covered in swastikas and all this muck and mire -
to be brought up out of that and be given a heart of flesh,
to come to know God as your Father and to have an intimate relationship
as a joint heir with Christ and His Kingdom is powerful.
This is more than just delivery from drugs.
This is deliverance; this is freedom.
This is what true power in love looks like in the flesh.
The Lighthouse Recovery Center is a place where great things have been going on.
We have a very special brother here who we partnered with.
We hosted a Back-To School Block Party and give-away.
Josh, tell us some of the things that we gave away at the block party.
Shoes, backpacks, food and T-shirts.
You allowed me to be a blessing and hand out to these children.
I had some kids crying because they have never received designer shoes in their life.
I was able to donate them and kids loved them.
Their response was great!
We all know how important those items are, especially to young children coming up in school.
I mean, the peer pressure and everything.
I went to a big city school and I’ve seen kids get their stuff taken from them.
Seeing these kids appreciate it like that – it is a gift from God.
Thank you very much for allowing me the opportunity to feel that kind of blessing.
We would like to thank the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua
and the Emmanuel TV Partners because you allow us to continue to help.
Here is our donation of $3,500 towards this ministry.
That is why it is so important for you to continue to give so that we can continue to help
The Lighthouse Recovery Center because they are reaching people and changing lives.
Our slogan is changing lives, changing nations and changing the world.
We can do these types of things together.
Just tell us how many men are here.
Between our two facilities, we have about 87 men.
We have about 40-45 women at the women’s facility.
We have transitional housing which I do not have those exact numbers for.
Those are for graduates as they leave the programme, to help them stay plugged in
because people are a lot more successful if they stay plugged into the ministry once they graduate.
We are trying to expand that and get more transitional housing for them
because right now, we don’t have enough for the amount of people we have.
We are trying to expand that; we are trying to grow
and with the way Emmanuel TV is helping us, we are going to keep going in the right direction.
Remember, we are changing lives, changing nations and changing the world.
TT ROBERT BEGIER 30/01/2019
RV: Mel Flowers 01/02/2019